due to the fact that the war between Russia and
из-за того что началась война России с
Ukraine began, everything became more expensive and
Украиной ээ дороже всё стало и тяжелее
life became harder, well, it was probably
жить стало ну тяжелее наверное скорее
more difficult for older people. Well, probably everyone felt
более взрослым людям Ну наверное всем
sorry for Lano. Of course, because the
Лано стало сожалея Конечно Потому что
sanctions, accordingly, the cost of everything
санкции соответственно стоимость на всё
has increased greatly, now inflation in the country
сильно возросла сейчас инфляция в стране
and therefore, of course, prices  everything
и поэтому конечно же цены на всё очень
has increased very much, that is, compared to
сильно возросли то есть по сравнению с
what it was even three years ago, but this is a
тем что было даже года три назад но это
direct This is a significant
прям Это весомая
difference
разница
Hello chat Let's talk
Здравствуйте чате Давайте поговорим
normally yes yes look I myself am from
нормально да да смотрите Я сам родом из
Rostov But  I’ve been living in London for 18 years, in 2
Ростова Но 18 лет живу в Лондоне через 2
years I’ll be
года буду
twenty Russian, but I’m a little more
двадцатом русский но я больше немножко
for Ukraine. Where are you from? We came from Russia from St. Petersburg
за Украину Вы откуда Мы с Питера из
to St. Petersburg or from there.
России приехали в Питер или оттуда
We live in St. Petersburg, were born in St. Petersburg.
ро Мы живём в Питере родились в Питере
either in the dorm
сес на хате у кого-то или в общаге
or who we are studying to be. I’m studying to be
да на кого учитесь мы Я учусь на
a conflict specialist and not a designer.
конфликтолога а не на дизайнера
It’s cool, all three of them are designers and you’re a
прикольно они все трое дизайнеры а ты
conflict specialist.
конфликтолог А почему именно
I don’t really know why it’s a conflict specialist.  I
конфликтолог на самом деле не знаю я уже
don’t like the university where
мне не нравится ну университет в котором
I’m currently studying, so I’m thinking of
я сейчас учусь поэтому я думаю
dropping out and maybe in another
отчислиться и может бы в другом
direction, it’s hard, it’s hard
направлении это тяжело тяжело
because I’m a psychology teacher,
потому преподаватель психологии
well, I’ll say this, conflictology is a
вот ну я скажу так конфликтология - это
very complex science if you take it so seriously
очень сложная наука если так серьёзно
Yes, but here now I’m very much a
рассматривать Да но у нас сейчас очень я
person who  doesn’t really like
вообще человек который не очень любит
history, but in terms of it, for me it’s kind of
историю но в плане для меня как бы мне
interesting to listen, just in communication.
интересно послушать вот просто в общении
But exactly how to study history is not my thing. But
Но именно как изучать историю не моё А
in conflictology, a lot of
вот в конфликтологии очень много
history is studied. That is, we have the history
изучается истории То есть у нас история
of conflictology, the history of Russia, the history of the
конфликтологии история России история
culture of St. Petersburg and for me  it’s
культура санкт-петербурга и для меня это
hard Because I can’t stand it and that’s
тяжело Потому что я не переношу это и я
why
поэтому
I understand it’s not a profile thing, but here What do the
Это не профильное я понял а тут О чём
girls talk about in chat roulette and
общаетесь девчонки в чат рулетке да о
a lot of things We communicate with many guys, both
многом Мы со многими ребятами общаемся и
the Chinese and the Koreans and the British
с китайцами и с корейцами и с британцами
and with whom we just haven’t talked in general  I’m
и с кем мы только общем не общались с я
half-brother because I’ve been living in Britain for 18 years, you
полубрат потому что я уже 18 лет живу в
can perceive me as a
Британии меня можете воспринимать как
British person well. Have you been to some
британца хорошо А вы были в каких-то
other countries? Besides Russia I’ve
странах других Кроме России Я очень
been to a lot of places.  e my parents,
много где была Я е у меня родители с
since childhood, probably from the
самого детства наверное где-то с
age of three months, took me around
трёхмесячного возраста водили и по
the countries of Europe and not only that is, I
странам Европы и не только То есть я
have visited a lot of places. But I don’t
много где побывала Но я не так много что
remember much that I was most likely only in Turkey
помню что я была скорее только в Турции
right now, let’s do this for the last 2
вот сечас давайте так вот последние 2
years  where were you girls in what
года где вы девчонки были в каких
countries? I was in Egypt a year
странах Я в Египте была года наза
ago, then I didn’t travel only around Russia,
дальше я не ездила только по России
but you’re only in Russia
тем А А вы только в России
now. Well, specifically, I
теперь Ну конкретно я ме из от выть я
can’t howl, but my father won’t let me.  you have
могу но ти отец типа не даёт вам
to go, like no, my father is like there are
выезжать типа нет у меня отец там типа
legal problems there, yes, he
юридически очень проблемы Да это па
was deceived for money and he is suing now, and
обманули на деньги и он судится сейчас и
due to the fact that he has courts, he can’t
в силу того что у него суды он не может
travel, it’s like now I’m
выезжать я как бы сейчас путешествую
only traveling around Russia from country to country, so
только по России по странам так А тебе
how old are you?  18 Well, you can already
сколько лет мне 18 Ну так ты уже можешь
travel regardless of di, I know, but I don’t
ездить независимо от ди я знаю но я не
want to, I want to see my region
хочу я хочу посмотреть свою рону в
where I live, look, you can’t
которой я живу посмотри то ты не можешь
go abroad because of debts
выехать за границу изза долгов
No no no I can, but I don’t really want to, and
Нет нет нет я могу но я не совсем хочу и
that’s a plus  My mother is expensive in terms of money. I
плюс это дорого денежно у меня вот мама
was recently in Turkey, but I myself, as it were,
Недавно была в Турции но я сама как бы
probably in the future I want to
потом наверное в будущем Хочу
travel Well, no no, that is,
путешествовать Ну не нет то есть когда
when they say Yes, what kind of problem with
когда говорят Да что типа проблема с
money I understand, yes, but when they
деньгами это я понимаю да но когда
say I don’t want to go It’s obvious [ __ ] here
говорят я не хочу ехать Это явно Бля тут
If I had money, I would
Если бы у меня были деньги я бы каждый
go to another country every evening, I
вечер ездил короче в другую страну я
say, I have several circumstances.
говорю у меня несколько обстоятельств у
I want to go with my family, but
меня Я хочу с как бы с семьёй ездить но
because of my father, I can’t go alone. I
у меня из-за отца не могу одна ездить Я
don’t want to, and what if I go alone?  I have the
не хочу и А если одно ехать у меня по
money Just
деньгам Просто
Wow, what do you think?  girls
Во а как вы считаете вот девчонки из-за
because I don’t quarrel Yes, it’s just a
того что я не ссорюсь Да вот просто
question because the war between
вопрос из-за того что началась война
Russia and Ukraine began, everything has become more
России с Украиной дороже всё стало и
expensive and life has become harder, well, it’s probably
тяжелее жить стало ну тяжелее наверное
more difficult for older people Well, probably
скорее более взрослым людям Ну наверное
everyone felt Okay, sorry Of course
всем Ладно стало сожалея Конечно Потому
Because sanctions cost accordingly
что санкции соответственно стоимость на
everything has increased greatly now, inflation in the
всё сильно возросла сейчас инфляция в
country and therefore, of course, prices for everything
стране и поэтому конечно же цены на всё
have increased very much, that is,
очень сильно возросли то есть по
compared to what it was even three years
сравнению с тем что было даже года три
ago, but this is really significant since I,
назад но это прям это весомая раз у меня
yes, have a father and mother in  They live in Rostov, and
да у меня отец и мать в Ростове живут да
then my mother says yes. Previously, I
то мама рассказывает говорит да Раньше
spent this amount there to buy
шла на эту сумму там с купалась
food, now for this amount, about
продуктов сейчас на эту сумму где-то
half of it, you can buy food like this,
половину можно продуктов купить вот так
and now now, in fact, 5,000
да сейчас сейчас на самом деле 5.000
rubles is nothing at all. Yes, she says,
вообще рублей ни о чём Да Она говорит
like, that’s so because  her pension is
типа это так потому что у неё пенсия
17,000, well, that’s actually funny, I’m just
17.000 ну это вообще смешная я просто
here from Britain sending help from
тут из Британии присылаю помощь с бате
his father. That is, she says: Yes, now it’s 10,000,
его То есть она говорит Да сейчас 10.000
even just like that in the store to go to the store to
даже вот так в магазине зайти чтобы
normally skimp for fruit
нормально скупиться чтобы фрукты ещё
some more to take everything and it flies away in one or two
какие-то взять всё та улетает на раз-два
Well yes Money flies away very quickly That
Ну да Деньги быстро очень улетают То
is, before you could
есть раньше можно было пакетов пять
easily get five packages, that is, like
вообще спокойно набрать то есть типа
some expensive food, straight meat, a lot of
какой-нибудь дорогой еды прям мяса много
seafood and so on with this money you can
морепродуктов и так далее на эти деньги
easily buy now  I’m saying,
спокойно купить сейчас вот я говорю Вот
I’m like a student, for example, just go and
я как студентка например сходить просто
buy some groceries, just cook for the evening,
продуктов купить вот чисто на вечер
for example, meat, and so on.
приготовить например мясо и так далее Ну
Well, you’re talking about nothing at all. Before,
вот ты д - это вообще ни о чём раньше на
you could easily buy enough groceries for a
ты д можно было спокойно продуктов на
couple of days. Well, that is, buy
пару дней Ну то есть купить абсолютно
absolutely now this  Of course it’s already hard with
точно сейчас это уже конечно тяжело с
this, that’s why  yes yes It’s interesting, but
этим вот поэтому да да Интересно а вот
the girls who are designers Yes, they work,
девчонки которые дизайнерами Да работают
and how much is the salary of designers in Russia
а сколько зарплата у дизайнеров в России
now? From eighty Well,
сейчас от восьмидесяти получается Ну в
depending on what, we have a
зависимости С чего то есть у нас как бы
designer, if in the workshop, but there are
дизайнера если в цех вот а есть
designers who draw and
дизайнеры которые шн которые рисуют и
who create with brands.  which in the
которые создают с брендами Вот который в
workshop is from 80 to 100,000 Wait in the workshop -
цеху от 80 до 100.000 Подождите в цеху -
this is what kind of designer what do you mean by
это какой дизайнер что имеется в виду
designer Well, you know, in terms of training, it’s
дизайнер Ну это знаете в плане обучения
like being given to a designer. But with us
как бы даётся дизайнера Вот Но у нас же
there are many, as it were, distributions where we are
есть много как бы распределений куда мы
yes this is a clothing designer you
да это дизайнер одежды вы вот это имели
meant this Yes yes yes Shriya there is a technologist
в виду Да да да шрия там технолог
designer fashion designer the designer himself
конструктор модельер сам дизайнер
who draws sketches this is all
который рисует эскизы вот это вот всё
together It goes there and as if in a workshop
вместе Туда входит и как бы если в цеху
then from 0
то от 0
you study to be a designer  clothes Yes, I
вы учитесь на дизайнера одежды Да всё
understood everything because I was a designer, I thought
понял потому что я дизайнер думал так
it was Burn everything I understand, this is a clothing designer,
это Горите всё Поня это дизайнер одежды
I understood I think that 8000 is what we are
я понял Я думаю что 8000 это мы сейчас
talking about now Judging by the fact that we live in St. Petersburg
говорим Судя по тому что мы в Питере
I think that in other cities
живём Я думаю что в других городах
others are much
другие намного
smaller  in Moscow there is more money But in
меньше в Москве коне побольше А вот в
others No
других
one will give you 8,800 dollars, it’s
Никто вам 8.800 долларов не даст это
somehow a little bit desirable. It seems to me Well,
как-то немножко желаемое Мне кажется Ну
this is not desirable, it seems to be stated
это не желаемое это как как бы заявлено
rather But in fact, real salaries are
скорее Вот Но по факту реальные зарплаты
completely
они абсолютно
different because Especially now with
другие потому что Тем более сейчас с
this crisis when  It turns out that
этим кризисом когда получается
some enterprises are closing;
закрываются некоторые предприятия
purchasing power is also, well,
покупательная способность также ну
clothes are also bought by someone. Yes,
одежда она же тоже кем-то покупается Да
if a person spends more on food. If a person spends more on food,
если у человека на продукты уходит
and
Ели у человека уходит на свет больше и
so on, Dasha, then he will have less
так Даше то у него на одежду меньше
left over for clothes, and you already  tried to work or
остатся а вы уже пробовали работать или
just the first
только первые
courses we don’t Here she works but she does
курсы мы нет Вот она работает но она в
n’t work in a coffee shop And in a coffee shop
кофейне работает не по А в кофейне
how much salary do
сколько зарплата
I get 3500 for
получается у меня 3500 за
3500 for a day shorter for a day 35
3500 за за день короче за день 35
dollars for 12 hours
долларов за 12 часов да
yes, well, I’ll now calculate it if for an
а ну я сейчас посчитаю это если на
eight-hour  a working day is shorter 23 it
восьмичасовой рабочий день это короче 23
turns out 3500 That is, it turns out If there
получается 3500 То есть получается Если
was an eight-hour working day it would
восьмичасовой рабочий день было бы это
be somewhere like
где-то было
22 like that 2150 even like that 21
бы 22 типа вот так 2150 даже вот так 21
dollars per  a working eight-hour day would be
доллар за рабочий восьмичасовой день был
Well, in fact, that’s 3,500 per working
бы Ну на самом деле вот 3500 за рабочий
day. This is still a good rate because
день Это ещё неплохая ставка потому что
I worked much less, I
я работала сильно меньше у меня
get 200 rubles per hour, I
получается за час было 200 руб я
worked for 14 hours. Well, that’s how we
работала по 14 часов Ну там вот и
calculate it, but I’m somewhere in the plus-  minus two
считаем но я где-то вот плюс-минус два
after two I worked 7 or 14 hours, I
через два я работала То 7 то 14 часов я
earned about 20,000 in a month, it’s generally such pennies
зарабатывала это вообще такие копейки
What, well, yes, 200 I ra in the summer for experience,
Что ну ну да 200 Я ра летом для опыта
roughly  saying that it was just like there
грубо говоря вот чтобы просто вот как бы
was some kind of well, I was
была какая-то ну я пыталась для себя
just trying to earn something for myself, but in fact,
просто там что-то заработать но по факту
everything that I earned was generally a
всё то что я заработала это вообще
complete yes. With all this, she worked
полный да При всём при этом она работала
at the rate for adults
по ставке для совершеннолетних потому
because she was at that  moment of being
что она была на тот момент
a minor Well, no, I worked
несовершеннолетни Ну нет Я отработала
like a minor Just a couple of weeks
Как несовершеннолетняя Всего пару недель
Well, in any case, like, well, like you Well,
Ну в любом случае типа ну как у тебя Ну
anyway The salary was just meager,
всё равно Зарплата была просто мизерная
that is, roughly speaking, I worked there for
то есть грубо говоря я там отработав
a month, I even got a little less than a month, I
месяц я вот даже чуть меньше месяца я
got 18 somewhere  600
получила вот 18 где-то 600
Yes, but here is the girl who is now the girl
Да а вот девушка которая сейчас девушка
who doesn’t work in coffee Do you
которая в кофе не работает Вы каждый
work every day or do you have like weekends
день работаете или у вас типа выходные
2 over 2 over That is, it turns out you
есть 2 над 2 над То есть получается вы
work 15
работаете 15
[music]
[музыка]
Well it turns out Well, the day when you
Ну получается Ну тот день когда вы
work it completely falls out for you
работаете он у вас полностью выпадает
Because  what if it’s 12 hours Work 8 hours
Потому что если 12 часов Работа 8 часов
you need to sleep somewhere at home Yes, it’s already 20 and
надо где-то дома поспать Да это уже 20 и
then the road there, that is, you
потом туда дорога туда то есть у вас в
don’t have anything left on time that day
этот день ничего не остаётся по времени
yes Well, yes I understand And so, for example,
выходит да Ну да А понял А так например
here you have it by the way  I know someone
вот у вас кстати из знакомых есть кто-то
who was taken to the war there or went to
кого там на войну забрали или пошл
earn money for the war, they seem to
зарабатывать на войну там же вроде
pay a lot of money there, they say from friends in
большие деньги платят говорят знакомых в
terms of some, you know, familiar parents,
плане какие-то знаете знакомые родители
something like that. But right from my
что-то такое А вот прямо чтобы из своего
social circle, I don’t have a classmate from Rostov.
Круга общения нет у меня из Ростова
Sanya Prokhorov sat with him
Одноклассник Саня Прохоров сидели с ним
at the same desk
за одной партой
died went and thought to earn money
погиб пошёл думал заработать бабки
in less than 3 weeks and that’s all they brought in. Well,
короче 3 недели и всё и привезли гро Ну
these are actually people who
это на самом деле люди которые
count on the fact that they will
рассчитывают на то что вот они там
work there, roughly speaking, there  they sign a
поработают грубо говоря там подпишут
contract and then work a little and
контракт и вот поработают немножко
get paid, but it doesn’t work like that in
получу деньги но это так не работает в
any country, it doesn’t work. If you kind of
любой стране не работает Если ты как бы
sign a contract, you’ll still get the
подпишешь контракт ты всё равно
maximum from the state. Even
государство тебя будет по максимуму Даже
if you return there, roughly speaking, with
если ты вернёшься там грубо говоря с
some kind of injuries,
какими-то ранениями
then the state will still take care of you.  will
и то всё равно тебя государство будет до
drag you to war until the last moment Unfortunately,
последнего таскать на войну К сожалению
these are simply the Rules of War in any country,
это просто Правила войны в любой стране
that is, like if everyone thinks that only
то есть Типа если все считают что только
in Russia such a story is of course
вот в России такая история Конечно же
not the same in Ukraine and in any other
нет так и на Украине и в любой другой
country, like if there is a war going on  in the country it’s all this without options There it’s bad for everyone, here’s how to explain it to you because I, for example, have a mother and father Yes, my mother is against the war And my dad is like that, he watches TV about Kyiv needing to be bombed there And that’s it, and here’s how you yes, you can see Why Russia attacked and why many people support this war, in fact, this topic of politics is very difficult But I could be wrong But this is my position, it’s clear that I am against war I am against any deaths because well, I It's a shame anyway, peace of mind  no
стране Типа если война идт в стране это
one is ever to blame for the World Cup. I think so, that is,
не виновато любое Я считаю так то есть у
here I once communicated with people,
нас вот я когда-то общалась с людьми
also in the same application, they directly
тоже в этом же приложении мне пря
proved to me that
доказывали что
this means any civilian population, even
вот значит любое мирное население даже
if they are against Well, like, or for, it doesn’t matter,
если оно против Ну типа или за неважно
they are all to blame, it’s not  so I think
они все виноваты это не так Я считаю
because when the war began, I
потому что вот когда началась война я
was still underage, I
была ещ несовершеннолетней я никак не
was not involved in this in any way, I understand why
была к этому причастна я понимаю почему
on the other
с другой
hand I understand on the other Rhone Why the
стороны я понимаю с другой Роны Почему
war began
началась война
because of a personal interest. That is, for example,
потому тельный интерес То есть например
for Russia, Ukraine in some way
для России Украина в каком-то плане
represented
представляла
its  now I beg your pardon, I
свои сейчас Прошу прощения
represented some kind of, roughly speaking,
представляла какую-то грубо говоря
security threat, that is, like,
угрозу безопасности то есть типа мы же
we don’t care anyway We are nothing with so many
всё равно Мы ничем с очень многими
countries, of course there we are all monitoring
странами конечно же там мы все следим за
what is happening on the border with
тем что происходит и на границе с
countries with which we have Gru
странами с которыми есть ним Гру
speaking, they stole
говоря укра
troops, they
войска они же
too  they tried, well, roughly speaking, Ukraine is
тоже пытались ну грубо говоря Украина
trying to join NATO and so on. That
пытается войти в НАТО и так далее То
is, I say again Zheki, I could be
есть я говорю опять Жеки я могу
wrong because I don’t understand
ошибаться потому что я плохо разбираюсь
politics well, that is, well, it’s just that my
в политике то есть ну у меня просто у
father says the same thing as
меня вот отец то же самое говорит что и
you Yes, my mother doesn’t But  father same thing NATO
ты Да мама не А вот отец тоже самое НАТО
biological laboratories, look, I can’t
биолаборатории вот смотри я не могу
understand, I
понять я его
ask him how Ukraine could attack
спрашиваю как Украина могла нападать на
us. If we are a nuclear power could not
нас Если мы ядерная держава не могла
attack us, but it was quite
нападать на нас но вполне это было
real, that is, Ukraine Russia put forward
реально то есть Украина Россия выдвигал
something like that, and Finland did the same thing, for
то что типа вот и Финляндии тоже самое
example. Well, why
например Ну почему же
did Finland strengthen its  borders with Russia
Финляндия усилила свои границы с Россией
because Finland has joined NATO
потому что Финляндия вступила в НАТО
now yes yes yes yes Russia She
теперь да да да да вот Россия Она же
understands that NATO troops are
понимает что натовские войска - это
always a huge threat to Russia Russia
всегда огромная Угроза для России Россия
is trying to protect its  some interests,
пытается защитить свои какие-то интересы
of course, I think that in any case,
конечно же я считаю что в любом случае
like Yes Sky,
типа об Да Скай до
goodbye, but bye-bye,
свидания а как бы пока-пока
so it’s
вот
clear that I think that
а Понятное дело что я считаю что не
people who say that
правы люди которые говорят что вот
Russia didn’t start the war, who objectively
Россия не начинала войну кто объективно
crossed the border, are wrong  it was Russia
как бы пересёк границу это была Россия
who started the war, it was Russia who attacked
кто начал войну была Россия кто напал на
another country, Russia is understandable, but
другую страну Россия это понятно но у
Russia also has its own interests. I think
России тоже же свои интересы Я считаю
that it’s still wrong to say
что тоже всё равно неправильно говорит
that well, we have a war there that’s a little bit
что вот ну у нас там война немножко
different, of course, for example,
чуть-чуть другая конечно же например по
compared to what  like World
сравнению с тем что как Вторая мировая
War II  in general, it’s even standing next to each other. But I think
это вообще даже рядом стоит Но я считаю
that we, if I may say so, more
что мы если можно так сказать более
democratically, for example, we’re fighting. But we
демократично например воюем Вот Но всё
still carry this too. And how more
равно это тоже несем А как более
democratic, look, if we’re hitting Kharkov,
демократично смотри если мы по Харькову
if we’re hitting the city of Bakhmut, here I have
лупим если мы город бахмут вот у меня
Sanya Prokhorov, this classmate, yes,
Саня Прохоров вот этот одноклассник да
he stormed Bakhmut  They
он штурмовал бахмут Они этот бахмут
razed 70,000 of the population to
70.000 населения было они сравняли с
the ground, there wasn’t a single house left
землёй там ни одного дома не осталось
alive, but that’s okay. It’s just that you
живого хорошо а то что О'кей Просто вы
support Ukraine that way.  No, I understand
так поддерживаете Украину Нет я понимаю
that every person has the right,
что у каждого человека есть право
look, I am against killing people, I am against
смотрите Я против убийств людей я против
us attacking Ukraine, I
того чтобы мы нападали на Украину Я
just don’t see why. Well, it makes no sense
просто не вижу почему Ну смысл нет то
that Ukraine, for example, has been in the Donbass for the
что Украина например на Донбасс те же
same 8 years. Bombed, I mean, no,
самые 8 лет Бомбила смысле нене так
look at it like that in the Donbass  Russian
смотри так на на Донбассе вот российские
troops captured Crimea in 1914
войска в четырнадцатом году захватили
Donetsk Lugansk I have a classmate
Крым Донецк Луганск У меня одноклассник
Sanya Prokhorov, he has been fighting since 1414
Саня Прохоров он с четырнадцатого года
they were in the Donbass well  Why
воюет они были на Донбассе хорошо Почему
no, it’s not quite like that Crimea, in fact,
нет не совсем так Крым по факту там же
I was there now I apologize We’re
была я сейчас Прошу прощения Мы у нас
just celebrating a birthday,
просто мы Праздновали день рождения
so I’m a little drunk so it’s
прошед поэтому я немножко пьяная поэтому
a little hard for me to reason And it’s
мне немножко тяжело рассуждать И строить
possible to formulate my own thought Well, you think that’s what
получается Ну вы считаете что вот то что
happened in Donbass in
было на Донбассе в этом полностью
Russia is completely involved in this in the Donbass because
замешана Россия на Донбассе потому что
look, it would be like if I didn’t know Sanya
смотри как бы вот если бы я не знал Саню
Yes, he still rests in peace already yes Well,
Да он ещ покоится с миром уже да Ну а
why are people then who are on  in the Donbass they are
почему люди тогда которые на донбасе они
overgrown, I’ll explain to you why, look.
зарос я тебе объясню почему смотри
Because when the Russian troops arrived
Потому что когда российски войска пришли
and the war began there, some went to
и началась там война часть уехала в
Russia, some went to Ukraine. Who
Россию часть уехала в Украину Да кто
could go where? Who had relatives where,
куда мог У кого где родственники были
of course, those who stayed there
конечно те кто остались там они ничего
will not say anything against Russia
не будут говорить против России потому
because for now  Russian troops there, you understand,
что пока российские войска там понимаешь
because there in the Donbass
потому что там на Донбассе и на подвалы
they threw people into basements and that’s all. Well, it’s
бросали людей и всё то есть Ну
lawlessness, here you are in Russia now, you can
беззаконие вот ты в России сейчас можешь
come out with a white piece of paper against the war, you
выйти с белым листочком против войны не
can’t, really, you’re going straight to the basement  they will throw
можешь правда тебя сразу на подвал кинут
it This will happen in any country if in
Вот это будет в любой стране если в
any country any any world it doesn’t matter
любой стране любое любой мир неважно
if any Civilian citizen says that he is
если любой Мирный граждан скажет что он
against the war against the state which
против войны против государства которое
is now there in such a difficult situation in one way
вот сейчас там в тяжёлой такой в такой
or another, it doesn’t matter if
или иначе какой-то ситуации неважно если
he comes out and says that he is against
он выйдет и скажет что он против
states anyway, one way or another, the
государства всё равно так или иначе
state in any country will be against
государство в любой стране будет против
this specifically no, see for example
конкретно этого нет смотри например
When America fought in Vietnam Yes in
Когда Америка воевала во Вьетнаме Да в
America there were anti-war rallies without
Америке были антивоенные митинги целые
anyone bothering people But in Russia yes for
бе людей никто не трогал А в России да
some reason, for example uh We have a
почему-то вот например ээ У нас
teacher at school  in Rostov Yes, which
учительница в школе в Ростове Да которая
we teach, well, she’s old and elderly, she’s
у нас учи ну же старенькая пожилая ей
70-something years old there. She came out with a sign.
там 70 с чем-то лет Она вышла с плакати
No to the war in Rostov. Yes, and she
ком Нет войне в Ростове Да и её в
was taken to the police and given a
полицию забрали и присудили штраф
huge fine, and so on, why is it good?
огромный и так дальше почему хорошо
Then why not, I’m just to  what do I
Тогда почему нет я я просто к чему имею
mean, therefore, as a person, if in you,
в виду поэтому как человек если у Вас
for example, in St. Petersburg, a person cannot, where there is no
например в Питере человек не может где
war, but come out and say something, like a
войны нету да выйти что-то сказать как
person in Donetsk will come out and say something
человек в Донецке выйдет и что-то скажет
against Russia; in principle, there
против России нас война в принципе в
cannot be a war in the country that  no
стране не может быть та что нет
goth, that's what I mean. Listen, look,
гот вот я имею в виду Послушай смотри
if you say Yes, you understand that a
если ты говоришь Да ты понимаешь что не
person cannot go out in St. Petersburg and be
может человек выйти в Питере и быть
against the war against Russia; the truth is, how
против войны против России правда то как
can a person in Donbass do this? Where there
человек на Донбассе это сможет где там
will be no limit at all; Ukraine; there are a lot of photographs;
будет Украина есть куча фотографий как я
Honestly, I’m not very much for
просто скажу честно что я не очень за
Ukraine Because when I drowned when
Украину Потому что когда я топила когда
I was I don’t know how old I am at that
мне было я не знаю сколько мне на тот
time, it’s honestly hard to read now
момент я честно тяжело сейчас прочитать
When the war started When else, in
Когда началась война Когда ещё в
principle, in Russia, here in major
принципе у нас по России вот по крупным
cities in Russia in St. Petersburg, exactly with us
городам по России по Питеру точно у нас
passed
проходили митинги
Navalny's rallies we had a huge
Навального у нас выходило огромное
number of
количество
people come out This is In what year Oh this is
человек Вот это В каком году О это ещё
when Navalny was still alive before he was
когда Навальный был жил до того как его
imprisoned This is in my opinion when
посадили это ещё по-моему когда
the war had just started when
только-только началась война когда вот
the rallies started I can't say
митинги начались я не могу сказать
wait no the war started in the
подожди нет война началось в
fourteenth  year you are talking about Which one are you talking about?
четырнадцатом году вы про Какой говорите
No, when did it start? Let’s say so.
Нет когда сво началось скажем так вот ко
So I was already sitting on Van when it
Так сво на Ване уже сидел когда сво
started. Not yet before the rallies took place.
началось ещ нет до того как митинги были
I don’t remember what year it was. I can’t
я не помню какой это был год негу
say, that is, in  They
сказать то есть вот в Питере вот
were passing through St. Petersburg, I know for sure, I was
проходили вот я точно знаю мне было лет
probably 15 maybe 16 years old, something in
наверное 15 может быть 16 что-то в
that area, probably yes 16, probably, that
районе того наверно да 16 наверно а то
is, somewhere, plus or minus two years ago. There
есть где-то плюс-минус года два назад
were rallies in our city, I
Вот были митинги У нас по городу я вот
was a witness, I was here  was harshly criticized
была свидетелем я вот была жёстко топила
for the fact that yes Navalny Well done Putin is
за то что вот да Навальный Молодец Путин
generally so bad No, I can’t
вообще такой плохой Нет я не могу
say that Putin is generally a
сказать что Путин вообще капец какой
great guy and a good President and so on,
молодец и хороший Президент и так далее
but I’ll tell you what we have When these events took place
но я вот что скажу у нас Когда проходили
rallies I drank very much for
эти митинги Я пила очень сильно за
Navalny, I wasn’t absolutely at that
Навального я вообще не абсолютно на тот
time, I didn’t even know anything from history
момент я даже ничего не знала из истории
at all, well, nothing, my father,
вообще ну ничего вот у меня отец
for example, he really supports
например он вот очень поддерживает
Russia, he’s the same thing, he grew up, he
Россию вот он то же самое он рос он
was born in the seventy-first year, he grew up in  The
родился в семьдесят первом году он рос в
USSR and the man saw how
СССР и человек видел как менялись
presidents changed, he saw what Putin did
президенты он видел что сделал и Путин
for the country and what what Medvedev was like and
для страны и что Какой был Медведев и
what Gorbachev was like and so on, he
какой был Горбачёв и так далее он
says I saw it all and he says that
говорит я это всё видел и он говорит что
I know what was with him And that is, like
я знаю что было при нём И то есть типа у
he has  what to compare it with  and he was in the army,
него есть с чем сравнить он и в армии
he himself came to the army, that is, he
был он сам пришёл в армию то есть у него
didn’t have that he was called up, there was no such thing,
не было что его призвали нет такого не
he came on his own, even for this, I
было он сам пришёл его даже за это я
remember that he said that he was
помню что он рассказывал что он его
praised, he was sent to Germany too,
хвалили он в Германию его вот тоже
he saw it all, he  I saw everything
посылали он это всё видел он все видел
political, how he himself went in the
политические как он сам пошёл в
Soviet Union, no one went himself, everyone was
Советском Союзе никто сам не шёл всех
taken into the
брали в
army, he himself went Well, I don’t know what
армии он сам шёл Ну я не знаю какой это
year it was, I can’t speak for him, but
был год я не могу же за него говорить но
here it is, as from his stories, he himself
вот он как из его рассказов он сам
came before his  here he is
пришёл до того как его вот вот он сам
came so look Wait, we’re not we’re
пришёл так смотри Подожди не мы мы
leaving from one moment you say
уходим от одного момента ты говоришь
Why do people in Donbass speak for
Почему люди на Донбассе говорят за
Russia because it’s good Why is it
Россию потому что хорошо Почему на
good in Ukraine Why did I just want to
Украине хорошо Почему я вот хотела
ask this question The topic
спросить этот вопрос просто Тема
changed Why in Ukraine people For
менялась Почему на Украине люди Вот
example, grandmothers are the same grandfathers
например бабушки те же самые дедушки
who are here  fought in the Second World
которые вот воевали во Второй мировой
War, why can’t they go out on
войне почему они не могут выйти и на 9
May 9, on May 8 there, roughly speaking, yes,
мая на 8 мая там грубо говоря да потому
because in Germany then it was May 8 in
что в Германии тогда было 8 мая на
Ukraine and growing up in Russia I understood the
Украине и на рос в России понял
early answer, see So  first
досрочный ответ смотри Значит первое
Let's set the record straight about the Donbass
Давай расставим точки про Донбасс Потому
Because you throw it out, you know, and don't respond
что ты накидывает знаешь и не отвечаешь
to it simply means about the Donbass Yes, if a
на просто значит по донбассу Да если
person in St. Petersburg cannot come out and
человек в Питере не может выйти и что-то
say something against Russia, then a person in the
сказать против России то человек на
Donbass Moreover, he will not say anything about
Донбассе Тем более ничего не скажет про
Russia, because Well, you  position that
Россию да потому Ну у вас позиция что
this is Russia there are troops in the Donbass because
это Россия там войска на Донбассе пому
Well, this is internationally recognized,
Ну это ж международно смотри
internationally recognized Yes, and Boin in what
международно признано Да и Боин в чем
year the holes are internationally recognized until now,
году международно признано норы до сих
look, tell me again  how Tell
счи смотри ещё раз расскажи как Расскажи
tell me how people in Donbass fought for 8 years
расскажи мне как 8 лет люди на Донбассе
without weapons against Ukraine how they didn’t
воевали Без оружия против Украины как не
just fight, wait, why did
воевали просто так подожди а почему
n’t Ukraine just go in and that’s it Well, I
Украина просто не зашла в и всё Ну я не
can’t say Well, look if Ukraine
могу же сказать Ну смотри если Украина
Yes, now, for example, troops entered the Kursk
Да сейчас например зашла в курскую
region Why?  she couldn’t,
область войсками Да почему она не могла
why did she just Bomb Donbass, why
почему она просто Бомбила Донбасс зачем
would she just come in, establish her
она бы просто зашла установила свой
control and
контроль и
that’s it? Well, I’m saying again that I can’t
всё Ну я же ещё раз говорю что я не могу
clearly judge, but I’m saying
чётко зать судить но я говорю
why Okay  but I, again,
почему Окей но я вот опять же таки мы
now we’re not even talking about Donbass No,
сейчас уже даже не про Донбасс не Нет
I just, I don’t understand how I can’t
просто я я не понимаю как я не могу
understand, my dad is constantly telling me, my
понять мне батя постоянно Смотри мне
dad is constantly telling me Ukraine Bombed the
батя постоянно говорит Украина Бомбила
Donbass, so I can’t understand, but Russia is
Донбасс вот я не могу понять вот Россия
not bombing St. Petersburg Why bomb
же не бомбит Питер Для чего бомбить
Ukraine had Donbass Well, this question should
Украине Донбасс было Ну это надо вопрос
be asked not to me clearly, but how is it that
задавать не мне явно ну как как это
Ukraine just takes over and bombs its territory
Украина просто берёт и свою территорию
What is the point Well, I don’t know, this
бомбит В чём смысл Ну я не знаю это
should probably be asked again Why ca
нужно наверное спросить ещё раз Почему
n’t they do it on May 9
на 9 мая не могут Подожди смотри давай с
Wait, look, let's go with Donbass with Donbass, that means Ukraine didn't Bomb Donbass now about May 9 Yes, I have relatives Yes, they live in Ukraine in the city of Kyiv, they come out normally, they sent photos, let's look Take it now, take it now, google it, I googled it, I also didn't believe in the attribution flowers Yes, flowers are laid on May 8 in Ukraine in Kyiv even now and veterans come out and And you manage to bomb these  Veterans' houses are theirs in
бомбить этих Ветеранов дома ихние в
Kharkov in bakhmut in
Харькове в бахмуте в
Zaporozhye in Ukraine every year and they
Запорожье в Украине каждый год да
celebrate in Russia just with veterans.
отмечают в России как раз с ветеранами
Soviet symbols have been banned in
делают Советская символика запрещена на
Ukraine for almost 9 years, everything is fine. Turn off the
Украине уже почти 9 лет всё пра Отключи
sound, look, look, Soviet symbols are banned in Ukraine,
звук смотри смотри на Украине запретили
sickly young stars,
советскую символику серпи молод звёзды
as well as swastikas because  that this
также как и свастики потому что это
totalitarian state
тоталитарное государство
was again, look girl, I’ll
было ещё раз смотри девочка я тебе ещ
tell you the story again, look in Ukraine
раз рассказу смотри в Украине
Yes  I was in Ukraine this year, I came to see Yes, I was at the parade on May 9 I was at the parade on May 9 in Kyiv Yes, no one said anything Yes, if you come with a swastika or with a five-pointed Soviet star, then yes, you can’t wear it, you need to take it off And so veterans come normally And you are a bomb, I understand correctly that you are asking these Veterans No, look, you tell me now, let’s now ask the Kazakh woman, the Kazakh woman, that you are against Germany
Да я был в Украине
Kazakh woman is not a Kazakh woman, she is what
казашка какой не казашка она какой
Look, you just go, I
Слушай иди ты просто я с казашкой
want to talk to a beautiful Kazakh woman, no who is with
красивой хочу поговорить нет кто небу с
you, not her, I want to talk to a pretty girl,
вами не она я с красивенько хочу
don’t worry, you’re the one Well, you, I
поговорить не волнуйся ты ту Ну ты Я
just admit it, you, yes, yes, I’ll
просто признай это ты да да да я с
talk to the beautiful one again, who
красивой поговорю юкой ещё раз кто
fought in the forty-first year, this is a simple
воевал в соро первом году это же простой
question for you, right Yes,
вопрос для вас правильно Да воевала
Ukraine fought and Belarus fought against
Украина и Беларусь воевала против
Nazi Germany and Russia, but it would have been a
гитлеровских Германии и России да было
wound like  Soviet and Russia didn’t
бы рана как советский а России не было
exist, your Russia didn’t have a country like that, you
не было вашей России страны такой не
understand everything, she appeared in the
было всё понимаешь она появилась десто
10th year Yeltsin invented you, Yeltsin gave
пер году Ельцин вас придумал Ельцин Дай
me a beautiful Kazakh girl. No, give me a
мне красивую казашку Нет ещё раз дай
beautiful Kazakh girl again, I’ll talk to her, you him.
красивую казашку я с ней поговорю вы его
Listen, I’ll tell you what, you
Слушай я тебе вот что скажу Ты
really thought  that you at least show
реально я думал что ты хоть покажешь
you understand
понимаешь
something was interesting but you are unrealistic you will
чтото интересно было но ты нереально ты
support people in
поддержишь людей в
Ukraine children in your arms they should be in
Украине детей на твоих руках они должны
your dreams You know the avenue of angels
сниться тебе они Ты знаешь аллея ангелов
Look how much Wow  Russians Yes,
Посмотри сколько Ух вами русскими Да
people, children in Ukraine and you sit
людей детей в Украине и ты сидишь такая
here smiling and telling me that in
тут улыбаешься и рассказываешь что
short there, even if in Ukraine they didn’t
короче там даже если в Украине не
let Veterans go somewhere. What business is it of yours to
пускали Ветеранов куда-то Какое вам дело
bomb Ukraine Come on, come on, the tape
бомбить Украину Давай ты
recorder is on Let’s go
Давай это магнитофон включился Поехали
further, subscribe to th Telegram directly at once
дальше подпишись на й Telegram прямо
VN axis and
зараз ось ВН а
Popik  It’s even more and more respectful YouTube
Попик це дуже и дуже важливо YouTube
has taken us through skarg or in your ban and there’s
заня нас через скарг ор в твый бан и
not even a lot of video  I show people
дуже багато видео не показую людям
constantly not showing information about streams
вчасно не показуе информация про стримы
so that we Mali operational
тому для того щоб мы Мали оперативный
link is written directly at the same time and Popik there
звязок пишиться прямо зараз а Попик там
in telegram okrim video sche tezh tsikava and
в телеграми окрим видео ще теж цикава и
korisna information and we are guilty of you trimati
корисна информация и мы повинни з вами
postiyny operational link
тримати постийний оперативный звязок
independantly in that chi show you about it
незалежно в того чи покаже вам про це
YouTube  Glory to Ukraine
YouTube Слава украини
subscribe
подпишись а